[Applause]
[Music]
well thank you
it's uh remarkable to see all of you
here in this amazing room
so uh well i hope we have a
an interesting and engaging time tonight
that's the plan i've got
i have a lecture planned so
it's got a strange title it's not that
exciting really
the first part of it is the
socialization of the value hierarchy
and the second is um and the
estimation of the magnitude of error
it's like you wouldn't think you'd come
and sit in here to listen to that
talk really would you i'm not sure i
would
but but it is interesting it's it's a
very very interesting problem
um and here here's part of what the
problem is the part of the problem i'm
trying to solve
part is part of it is um
how is your emotional stability
tied up with your social identity that's
a really important question
and and i i think it might be the
central question that i've been pursuing
my entire my as long as i've been able
to think intellectually that might be
the problem that i've been pursuing
because
one of the things i've been interested
in is why is it that people are
so committed to their group identity
let's say or their or their group
beliefs
that they will well let's say go to war
to protect them
or to spread them or that they will
commit atrocities
hypothetically in defense of them so
it's a very interesting problem
um you know because people when when
people think about
the motivation for war for example they
often attribute it to economic causes
and
that just never struck me as as
plausible sometimes it's plausible but
um it's not it's not a deep solution as
far as i'm concerned
it's more psychological it's our beliefs
are important to us
and what does it mean well there's a lot
of questions there
what do you mean by belief exactly
um you know physicists generally don't
go to war over their belief
in one physical theory over another so
it can't be just as simple as belief it
has to be more complicated than that
and um and
and and and people are committed to
their beliefs too and it and it isn't
obvious what commitment means
and so those are the things that i've
been
trying to unpack what does it mean to
have a belief
and what does it mean how does it how
does it how does it
why is it important to you why is it
crucial to you there's something
associated
deeply there's a deep association
between belief and
value and so then that brings up another
question
what exactly do you mean by value so
that's that's three hard questions
and so that's part of it and then
so that's the value hierarchy question
part of it and and then the
error magnitude problem is um well let's
say
let's say you go to a party and
you tell a joke and uh
you know you think it's pretty funny
joke and
you tell your joke and no one laughs
and in fact they look at you like you're
rather odd
and then the question is well how how
should you respond to that
like what exactly does that indicate
about you i mean does it indicate
a minor flaw in an otherwise stellar
personality
because that's a possibility or does it
mean that like you're
a creep right and maybe right down to
the core
and you know you could even
you could even think the less that you
think that it means that you're a creep
the more likely it is that you are
one so but you know it's it's very hard
to estimate
the magnitude of an error we have how
upset
should you get when something that you
don't want to happen
happens and it's very very hard to
figure that out if you wake up in the
morning and
you know you have a pain
say in your side um or you're not
feeling particularly well
it's like well how upset should you get
about that
and one answer is well
like maybe you're gonna die in three
months you know maybe that's the
beginning of pancreatic cancer and
that's the end of you and so maybe you
should just be
terrified into paralysis when you have a
pain that you can't explain or maybe you
should just
brush it off and think well you know
i'll get up and
do what i usually do and it's probably
nothing and
sometimes you're right with the it's
probably nothing approach and sometimes
if you don't go to the physician
right away because you have some
relatively trivial pain
then you're dead and so
this problem of estimating
magnitude of error importance of error
is it's unbelievably it's unbelievably
difficult problem and so i want to
address
both of those problems at the same time
tonight so that's the plan
so we'll see how that goes so
and then i i want to weave in there one
more thing which is
this this relationship between your own
psychological structure
whatever that happens to be your own
value hierarchy because there's there's
a very tight relationship between your
value hierarchy
and your psychological structure which
is why hierarchies by the way which
are necessary which is part of the point
i was trying to make say in rule one in
twelve rules for life when i talked
about hierarchies there's no getting
away from hierarchies
as a hierarchy is a structure that tells
you that one thing takes precedence over
another
that one thing is more important than
another right and if
everything is of equal import then
nothing is more important than anything
else by definition and then
well what should you do and the answer
is
well you can't tell because nothing is
any more important than anything else
and
the definition of important
fundamentally
is something like that which you should
do first
you know that constitutes importance um
that's also something that's relevant i
would say too because
um a lot of the way that we look at the
world is as a place to
we look at the world as a place in which
to act and we make a lot of judgments
about
the nature of the world in terms of how
we should structure our action
in fact the theory that i am putting
forth in general
is a theory that's predicated on the
notion that
the essential way that we look at the
world is
as if it's a forum of action like a
dramatic
forum like a story that that that's a
good way of thinking about it that
we really do view ourselves and our
place in the world
as a story that's set in a lan in a
narrative landscape
and you know you might argue that that's
not the case you could say with that
viewpoint for example has been
superseded by a scientific viewpoint
but it isn't obvious to me that that's
the case and it
certainly isn't it's certainly not the
case that we act that way
and it's certainly not the case that we
structure our political systems that way
treat each other that way or that we
think that way
or that we react emotionally that way
and so that's a lot
and you know it's also the case that the
other thing that's worth thinking about
in this regard is you know we've only
been thinking about the world
as an objective place for
500 years something like that i mean
maybe you could chase it back to the
ancient greeks and go back 2 000 years
but
whatever from a from from a historical
perspective
500 years or 200 years is the same
amount of time
and it's a tiny fraction of the amount
of time that
living creatures that were approximately
like us have been around
so we got along fine without thinking
about the world as an objective place
for
a very very long time we survived and
here we are
it doesn't mean it's a bad idea but it
it does
imply that there are other ways of
looking at the world
that are highly functional and that have
been conserved for
well for let's say for evolutionary
reasons and so you know if you
make the case which you might that
what you evolve to match
is reality at least you match it well
enough so that reality doesn't kill you
which is more or less the definition of
evolution if you
evolve to match reality in some
sense and the manner in which you evolve
predisposes you to view the world as if
it's a narrative
of sorts then possibly
the world is a narrative of sorts at
least
in so far as it concerns you now what
that means metaphysically i don't know
but that's okay because
who knows anything metaphysically
virtually by definition
what's metaphysical is beyond what you
know you can speculate
but and and and and so you know i would
speculate that
there is something narrative about the
structure of the world but it doesn't
matter
we don't have to go down that route we
can we can just think about this
practically
so the first thing i want to tell you
about that i think is really
important to lay out the structure of
this argument is something about the
relationship
between perception and
emotion and motivation and this is
actually pretty simple
and but people don't know it
and i guess it's simple in the way that
complex things are simple when you think
them through for a very long time
and understand them and then can finally
lay them out
you know in some manner that's rather
let's say clear because you understand
them
i i derived a fair bit of this
information
from a book called the neuropsychology
of anxiety by a man named jeffrey gray
who i think was
one of the two greatest
neuropsychologists of the 20th century
two or three um and uh
that his neuropsychology of anxiety
which is on my list of recommended books
by the way on my website
it's a really hard book like it's like
and i mean it's a
it took me like it took me like six
months to read that book
and all of it was painful and
the reason for that was well you know
book books are interesting
um some some aren't um
um often i um dog-ear the pages of
books that i'm reading if i find a line
or something you know that i'd like to
remember that i think is
important and you know i have some books
on my shelves that like
pages are dog-eared double because there
was a really amazing thought on one page
and there was a really amazing thought
on another on the other page
right you know the facing page and so
the whole damn thing is just nothing but
dog ears
and then there's other books where
there's zero
um when i read nietzsche for example
there was lots of dog ears
on beyond good and evil which is a great
book and nietzsche actually
he came up with the most arrogant
statement anybody ever made about
about himself as an author which is
really quite impressive
to to come up with the most arrogant
statement you know that's really
something and
he was he was great at coming up with
one-liners philosophical one-liners
he said um i can write in a sentence
what other people what it takes other
people
a book to write and then he said no they
know that they can't even write in a
book so that's pretty good eh it's like
arrogant and then he topped it it's like
yes this is a man who could
who could really write anyways um the
problem with reading a book like that
beyond good and evil say is that every
damn
sentence is a thought and a
deep thought and so reading beyond good
and evil it's like just
constantly being punched i mean partly
you're punched because you read
part of it you don't know what the hell
he says and so then you know you're
stupid and so that's a punch
and then and then and then now and then
you stumble across something you
understand and it's like
it's hard on you he said he
philosophized with a hammer you know
that he was breaking things apart and
and and there's no doubt about that so
now and then you run across something
you understand and
and then that breaks you apart because
you understand it and so
and it takes a long time to go through
the book because you have to think about
it
and and and god that's not good thinking
about things
you know well it isn't because you know
when you think about you already know
everything in some sense you know you've
got a map that covers the whole world
which is sort of why you can function
and so as long as everything's going
fine you don't really have to adjust
your map and
you don't have to think but then if you
come across something
that makes you think then what that
means is that part of
the way you were thinking was wrong and
so
when you think something when you're
forced to
then some little part of what you were
your map the way you represent the world
it has to die because it was wrong and
then it has to be replaced by this new
thing and
god only knows how much of what it was
that was there has to die that's part of
the magnitude of error problem and so
people don't like to think and so it's
hard to read difficult books
like beyond good and evil because you're
just forced to
think and think and it's just exhausting
you wish you wish that he would just
go away you know which is why they're
trying to not
teach difficult books in universities
anymore so that people don't have to
undergo the
difficult process of actually having to
think and transform themselves anyways i
read jeffrey gray's book
the neuropsychology of anxiety and
it was like that he he was he was
something man
student of a psychologist named hans
isaac
who was the most cited psychologist in
the 20th century
and and really quite a good psychologist
he laid a lot of the groundwork for
modern
theories of of temperament and
personality they've been modified since
his work but
he got extroversion right he was the
first person to really identify
extroversion
in a manner that could be measured carl
jung actually invented the notion but
isaac figured out how to measure it
which is a big deal and he also
noted that there was another important
personality dimension neuroticism which
is the tendency towards negative emotion
and he got that right too because that
actually happened to be the case and he
figured out how to measure it so
isaac was the first person who really
established um
conceptually the fact that our two
fundamental we have two fundamental
emotional systems one positive and one
negative
that they weren't they're not opposites
exactly
they're actually separate biological
systems so some people can be
extroverted which means they're quite
happy and
assertive they smile a lot they laugh a
lot they tell a lot of jokes they like
to party
they always like to be around people
that's a extroverted person
and they can also be unhappy worried
anxious depressed frustrated
disappointed i mean living with someone
like that's quite a trip
because they're just all over the place
but you know
but there are people like that because
you can be high in negative emotion and
you can be high in positive emotion or
low in both or whatever
and it's useful to know that it's useful
to know that about your partner
um and about the people around you and
if you are interested in this sort of
thing by the way um
i have a personality test online
uh at understandmyself.com and you can
go there and
it takes about 15 minutes and it gives
you five
dimensions of personality uh
extroversion neuroticism that's positive
and negative emotion
agreeableness which is uh like uh
it's probably the maternal instinct
dimension
but it but at least it's the variance
between compassion and competitive
aggression
it's something like that and that looks
like a continuum and there's another
dimension which is
trait conscientiousness which is
integrity and
and uh and dutifulness um orderliness
industriousness
and then finally an uh the fifth
dimension which is
openness which is like a hybrid between
intellect
intelligence roughly and creativity and
so you can go there and find out how you
compare to other people and that's kind
of interesting and
useful because it's kind of useful to
know who you are
and to to know that that's actually who
you are you know that you have a nature
and
some some of that stuff's movable but
it's not as movable as you think and
the farther you want to move it the
harder it is to move like you can take
an introvert
um you know you're an introvert if
you're if when you're around people
you get exhausted by it you have to go
off by yourself and recover you know
then you're an introvert and if you're
an introvert you don't really like being
in groups and so sales you know
maybe that's not for you you know um and
that's a good thing to know because
if you're an introvert why go be a
salesperson and be miserable
do some do something where you can spend
time alone and not be miserable
that's better you might as well match
your occupation to your temperament
rather than the other way around now you
know you can take an introvert
um i've worked with lots of introverts
who who
say had made pretty good progress in
their careers and they were at a point
where they had to do a lot of social
networking
you know and otherwise they were going
to hit a plateau in their career
and they could be taught the skills of
extroversion
sort of one at a time rather painfully
so they could learn them they could
accrue the skills and that would
broaden their personality outward into
the say extroverted end of the
continuum but it didn't make them
extroverts
and so they were still temperamentally
introverts and so you know if you're a
neurotic person high negative emotion
you can you can learn to regulate your
anxiety and so forth and
and and and but you hit a point of
diminishing returns
and and it's and it's difficult it's
effortful
so anyways back to isaac and then back
to
jeffrey gray so isaac identified
extraversion and introversion or
extroversion and neuroticism and that's
going to be very important in a minute
and gray um elaborated isaac's theories
to a large degree but he did that
neurologically he he was a he was a
master of the animal experimental
literature
and a lot of that's being phased out of
universities because the
regulations for animal experimentation
have become so onerous
and difficult that it's much easier for
beginning
scientists just not to bother
and that's a real catastrophe because we
have learned a lot about the brain
in the last 50 years a lot and we've
learned
very little about the brain from pet
scans and mri scans and
like that complicated technology that's
used to study human beings and
an unbelievable amount by studying
animals and you might think rats in
particular
and you might think well you know rats
why
they're not much like human beings you
know but but that's
wrong um um you share i don't know what
it is
98.5 of your genetic structure with rats
some of you probably more than that um
and and you know we we haven't
devolved from the common ancestor with
rats from an evolutionary perspective
that long ago i mean like it's millions
of years ago you know but
it's it's short compared to how long ago
we devolved
let's say from or we we yeah devolved i
think that's
good enough from amphibians and so we're
a lot like rats man and we have the same
skeletal structure and our brains are
quite similar and the neurochemistry is
very very very similar i mean the
neurochemistry is similar right down to
the level of crustaceans which is why i
wrote about lobsters in
rule one because our because i thought
it was so bloody amazing when i came
across that literature to see that
um when lobsters are defeated in a
social contest
and they lose their hierarchical
position that they undergo
neurochemical changes that are analogous
to the neurochemical changes that human
beings undergo
that's so amazing and that the same damn
drugs that help
us antidepressants essentially also
cheer up defeated lobsters i mean it's
such a
it's a staggering demonstration of the
continuity
of biology across you know span
unbelievable spans of time you know
critics have
complained that i cherry-picked the data
but they don't know what the hell
they're talking about
so they don't they don't i studied the
serotonin system for a very very long
time
and i know perfectly well that one of
the things that it does
is monitor your position
in a social hierarchy and and and
and it's more important than that
because the serotonin system
is a it's a master control neurochemical
system
it's like the conductor of an orchestra
everything in your brain depends on the
serotonin system which is why
you think about it like an
antidepressant um
decreases the rate at which neurons will
reuptake
serotonin you need serotonin to modulate
the way your neurons work
you take an antidepressant and the
serotonin works a little longer
okay so what's the consequence of that
well let's say you're depressed
okay we've got to think about being
depressed for a minute so when when
you're depressed this is what happens
all you remember about the past is
what's negative so everything about the
past is negative
all you can see in the present is what's
negative
everything about the present is negative
and
nothing about the future is positive at
all and so so that's interesting a
because it means that something has
shifted
inside you let's say
neurophysiologically
that changes the way you view everything
everything your entire past the present
and the entire future
and what it essentially does is
exaggerate negative emotion to a
tremendous degree that's depression
and suppress positive emotion now there
can be variants in that
sometimes you see depressed people and
they come you can think about your own
mood in this way you know
you might say well i'm not that sad but
i've just sort of lost my interest in
everything
okay so that means that what's happened
is your positive emotion system has been
suppressed
because the positive emotion system is
what gives you that
interest in things that pulls you
forward to action
okay and the negative emotion system
that's
anxiety that's a huge part of it
frustration disappointment grief
pain that kind of covers it anger is
well though anger is a bit complicated
because it's half a positive emotion and
half a negative emotion which is why it
feels so good to get angry
by the way and why it also impels you to
action whereas most negative emotions
stop you
you know so so in in any case
um if you're if your serotonin system if
your serotonin function
declines then all of a sudden everything
is negative
you think well isn't that interesting
how the hell can it be that
something can change within you that
changes everything
and the answer has to be well it must be
a fundamental system that's been
changed right because if it changes
everything
it has to be a system on which all other
systems
depend and that is the case with the
serotonin system
and that's really worth knowing
especially when you also know that the
serotonin system
counts where you are in the social
hierarchy and so there's this weird kind
of one-to-one correspondence
imagine a social hierarchy has 10 levels
i don't care what
hierarchy you're in most people's
hierarchies are actually quite small
they sort of consist of the people that
they compare themselves to
you know which is a strange thing too
because one of the things that you see
happening with really successful people
is
they actually don't get a lot more
lot happier and a lot less unhappy as
they climb the
the broad social ladder because the
people they compare themselves to
change and so i can tell you a funny
story about this
so i know this guy i worked with him for
a long time his name is adeoresi
and he's a hell of a guy he's like six
foot seven and he's like really
charismatic and
and he's been pretty successful he built
this company in in san francisco called
founder institute
and it's only one of many things he's
done and um
it's operating in 165 cities
it's a school to teach people how to be
entrepreneurs he's trying to export
silicon valley
um what would you call it know how
technological and
and financial to the rest of the world
and in like five years he built 165
schools not not physical schools but
school-like
organizations around the world and like
go go try that
like that's really hard you know just to
build one is hard but to do that in
multiple languages all over the world
it's bloody well impossible and then
at the same time he built his
organization
started 2500 successful companies as a
consequence of
of building this school it's that's
pretty good you know and
and and he was having a rough time and
was talking to me on the phone
um about about you know he wasn't so
happy about what he'd done with his life
and he said geez
i compare myself with my roommate and
you know i've hardly done anything and
his roommate was elon musk
it's like i just laughed at him i
thought geez
really that's what you're gonna you
haven't done anything compared to elon
musk
and you're depressed about it it's like
yeah well you and the rest of the planet
i mean look
what it must must what did he do he
invented an electric car
that's impossible then he made it work
that's impossible
and then he built an entire
infrastructure to charge it
and and and that worked and that's
impossible
and then and then they're good cars and
and then he made them faster than any
cars have ever
been and cheap and so that's impossible
and then that wasn't good enough so then
he decided that he would compete with
nasa which is impossible
and build rockets at one tenth the price
they were building them except bigger
and then he would shoot his car on his
rocket out into space
right and he did all that and it's like
a day i was thinking i've hardly done
anything with my life
it's like oh so but my point is is that
you know
you you primates of our type
sort of have an a group size that we
think about as our group of about 200
people so like
on facebook for example the probability
that you're in
something approximating reasonable
constant
communication with more than 200 people
is low
you just don't have the time and you
can't keep track of it so
so our natural group is something like
200 and
our groups tend to fragment when they
get bigger than that and so and that's
also
associated by by the way with cortical
size you see this in primates is that
as primates get developed larger brains
this the
group size that they seem to be able to
manage also increases and
that might be part of the reason why
they develop larger brains
who knows but anyways it's about 200
people
and the problem is is that as you get
more successful say
in in the global hierarchy of
uh 100 million people the 200 people
that you compare yourself
changes and so that you end up with 100
million dollars
and you're not very happy because your
50 billion yacht is like 20 feet shorter
than
your friends you know 150 million dollar
yacht and
so and you're high in neuroticism so
that makes you frustrated and
disappointed you know
so anyways anyways it's important it's
important
to understand it's the the the message
here the point of this is that
you have a system the serotonin system
base of your
neural physiology it also sets your
brain up during embryonic development
so it's it really is it's really is the
master control system
in many many ways and
it counts where you are in your
hierarchy
and then it decides how much positive
emotion and how much negative emotion
you should feel
on average because of your position
and so like if you're let's say number
one is at the top and number 10 is at
the bottom so you're number 10
you're barely clinging to the bottom of
reality your brain says look it's
dangerous where you are at the bottom of
the hierarchy you don't have a lot of
friends
it's uh it's precarious down there and
so that means any little thing that goes
wrong
any little error you make that might be
the end of you and so
you better be on guard and alert and if
something small happens
it it better hurt because it might be
the
straw that breaks the camel's back and
there's nothing pleasant about that like
of course why would there be why would
there be anything pleasant about
us a process that magnifies
everything negative you feel about
anything that might be wrong and and not
just on
not just on one small dimension of
negative emotion not just
anxiety which is bad enough but anxiety
and the pain related emotions so
pain related emotions are pain obviously
that it generally indicates damage to a
psychophysiological system
but grief is a pain-like emotion and
frustration is a pain-like emotion
and so is disappointment loneliness as
well those are all
pain-like emotions and have elaborated
out of an underlying pain system and
the so the negative emotion system is
like a tree that has branches
and each of the branches is the separate
negative emotion you know but they're
all tied together at the root and
positive emotions are like that as well
except they're not quite as
differentiated
and so if your serotonin levels fall
because you've suffered a
hierarchical defeat then the positive
emotion system gets flattened so that
good things no longer feel good because
it's dangerous to take risks perhaps if
you're at the bottom of the hierarchy
and you're not doing very well which is
why you're at the bottom why should you
have any trust in yourself
and you don't have any friends and
you're not well situated in
in the social world you're not going to
be enthusiastically
moving forward to do new things and so
your motivation for
for for engaging in life declines and it
can decline pretty much to zero you know
if you
if you see people who are seriously
depressed they say well i can't even
listen to music anymore
it just sounds flat and dead you know
and you know if you talk to someone who
says that about music they're
they're pretty damn depressed because
music is one of those things that
virtually everybody always enjoys you
know at least
one genre or another and and you know
the
depressed person will describe even that
the sensory quality has changed
and so and then they also say they're
absolutely overwhelmed with negative
emotion
and so okay so that's a good thing so
that's that's a good
very interesting thing to know is that
your
the manner in which one of your
fundamental neurochemical systems
is tracking your position in a hierarchy
is crucial to the maintenance of your
emotional stability okay so
so so so now you want to keep you want
to keep that in mind because that's the
first important point okay so now
now the next thing i'm going to do is
explain to you
how it is that the way you look at the
world
is related to the emotions that i just
described and then i'm going to talk
about how that
in itself is related to the idea of
hierarchy
and and and we're gonna we're gonna
we're gonna explore from there
so when you look at the world you don't
you see you think that the world is made
of
obvious objects and that you look at
them
and then you think about what they are
and then you think about how
you evaluate them and then you think
about how you use them and then you
decide to act
and that's not the case because the
world doesn't come
segregated neatly into objects
and it took people a long time to figure
this out because
when you look at the world there it is
segregated neatly into objects right it
takes no effort at all except takes half
your damn brain to do that
right and we're very visual creatures we
have great visual systems
and and and so a tremendous amount of
metabolic energy and evolutionary uh
uh expenditure of time has gone into
providing us with a visual system that
just breaks the world up into obvious
objects for us
and it isn't that isn't even right
because we don't actually see
objects what we see are more like tools
and obstacles
we just think they're objects like when
you come in here i can give you an
example of that
okay think about a bean bag okay
i think about a stump and think about
a stool say those are all chairs
okay it's like what do you mean they're
all chairs what do they have in common
objectively speaking a bean bag doesn't
have legs
you know a stump is rock hard and solid
a stool is is something almost
completely unlike a beanbag
well they're all chairs well why well
the answer is
you can sit on them and so most of the
things that we group together as
objects we group together as a
consequence of functional utility
and not because they share a set of
features of
that are objectively similar and the
reason that we perceive
in that manner is because we don't
really care that much about the
objective features of the world
because we have to care about being
alive and so what we actually care about
is what
things do and so we tend to
see things that do things and group
together perceptually things that do
things and so
you know when you walk into a room like
this there is a trillion things you
could look at
you could look at the color variation in
the carpet forever
you know if you if you came in here on a
psychedelic you might even do that
right well it's interesting because one
of the things psychedelics do is
they they decrease the degree to which
you view the world in an iconic manner
and then you see the incredible
complexity
that's underneath everything and it's
absolutely fascinating
now it's not good because you shouldn't
come in here and just look at the carpet
for an hour you know it's
it's it's not that productive unless
you're trying to equate yourself
re well re re-equate yourself with the
fundamental wonder of the world you know
and
there is some utility in that artists do
that but practically speaking it's not
that useful
what happens when you come in here you
know you have a goal in mind you you're
going to watch what happens on the stage
you're going to listen
and so you only see what's relevant to
that and so what you see are chairs and
chairs are things you
sit on and so they pop up into your
perceptual field just like that and then
you you know what to do with the chair
you sit on it and
partly the reason you know what to do
with the chair isn't because you look at
the chair and you think oh look a chair
because you didn't do that when you came
in here right now there wasn't a single
one of you
that came in here and looked at at the
rose here and said
oh look chairs right it's it's
self-evident that they're there
what happens is that you look at the
chair and it maps
the the chair maps itself onto your body
like you prepare yourself that the
perception prepares you
for the action so as soon as you see the
chair which has a certain shape
so imagine it's a pattern that sustains
itself in time
right because that's what a chair is
it's a pattern that sustains itself
across time
and that pattern is transformed into a
pattern of light and then that's
transformed into a pattern on your
retina
and that's transferred into a pattern on
your optical nerve and then that's
transferred into patterns all over your
brain
and some of those patterns are the
patterns that allow you to perceive
the chair consciously and some of them
are patterns that enable your body to
prepare
to take this position in the chair
because part of what your eyes do
is map right onto your motor system so
that you look and you know what to do
and it makes you a lot faster right you
look at something you know what you're
supposed to do with it your body's
prepared to do it
and that and that's kind of also what it
means to understand something
you know if you look at it and you know
what it is
you know how to use it it means you can
just map the thing right onto your body
and so some people people are people are
very very good at that and and
especially as you develop expertise at
something you just get better and better
and better at that
there are people that have certain forms
of brain damage um
lermite syndrome i think it was called
if i remember
correctly also known as utilization
syndrome and these are people who have
a degeneration of the prefrontal cortex
which is the part of your brain
that organizes your behavior i would say
at the highest level of abstraction so
when you're thinking voluntarily about
what you might do
and then you go do it it's your
prefrontal cortex that's
thought that up voluntarily and then
organized the rest of your brain to go
do it and so
it kind of one of the things it does is
inhibit
all the other things you might do so one
of the things that happens to people who
have prefrontal damage
especially if it's on the right hand
side is they get very socially
inappropriate
because they have all sorts of whims and
motivations and emotions
that would normally be inhibited by you
know attention to context let's say and
and the desire for voluntary activity
and they lose that part of the brain and
so they get
they get disinhibited they can get
disinhibited to the point where they
have to be
institutionalized or jailed because they
start acting so inappropriately that
they can't be
controlled and so anyways lermit
syndrome is utilization syndrome and
one of the things that happens to people
who have utilization syndrome
let's say they're in an old folks home
maybe it's consequence of a degenerative
neurological disease and they're walking
down the hallway and there's an
open door and they walk through it
they can't help it because what do you
do with a door that's
open you walk through it now you don't
if you're doing something else right
but if you're not doing something else
because you haven't got the part of you
that
is helping you do something else then
the object just tells you what to do
you know and you see this with little
kids too because whenever
you present them with an object you know
they grip they
grab it right away they often grab it
and put it in their mouths and they do
that because their mouths are already
wired up
completely when they're born right but
from a sensory perspective and from a
motor perspective and so kids are always
cramming things into their mouth
so that they can investigate them with
their tongue and map what they are
it's important for them to well that's
how they learn about the world
and so anyways if you have utilization
syndrome
you can't not utilize things so you can
hand someone
a bottle or a cup of water who has
utilization syndrome and they're not
thirsty and they'll drink it because
it's a cup of water and what is that
it's not an
object it's a thing to grip and
drink you know and it's it's how else
can you look at this uh
this isn't a cliff it's a falling off
place
right and if you're if you're one of
those strange creatures who just think
it's a cliff
and and and you know you're i don't know
what you're abstracted in thought and
you walk off it then you're dead
it's a lot better to perceive it as a
falling off
place which is what you do because you
know you you know what it's like you
go somewhere that's steep and you kind
of play with the edge a little bit and
you can feel the
falling off place map itself on your
whole body it's
it's kind of a strange i suppose
an interesting experiment to play with
that you you know
you might be back here and you think
yeah that's not too bad i wonder if i
can get a little closer
you know and and maybe you can and maybe
you can get well maybe you can get too
close
and then you're an evolutionary mistake
so
but but you know you get you get
close enough maybe you peer over and
think yeah that's enough
and you can feel the falling off place
map itself onto your body and
that's you perceive with your emotions
and your motivations
and your action systems way more than
you think
so you don't it isn't object picture on
your eye
picture in your brain thought emotion
and then action that that's not how it
works you're you're representing the
world
at multiple levels in your nervous
system
at the same time and and and you need to
and one of those levels is emotional so
okay so
here here goes for the emotional part
now look
um and this is this is just as important
as the
serotonin idea i would say which means
it's really important because the
serotonin idea is really important to
know that
your position in the social hierarchy
determines the balance between your
positive
and negative emotion that's like a
crucial insight into
human behavior and and that we have a
positive emotion system
and that we have a negative emotion
system and that they're separate
those are unbelievably important um
important discoveries all all made by
the way virtually all made by animal
experimentalists
just so you know because they deserve
some credit um so
now the the issue is how is your
perception
related to your emotion and so it looks
like it
and this is much much of this i learned
from jeffrey gray
now gray was a student of isaac but he's
also a student of someone named norbert
weiner
who was a uh cyberneticist
at mit he established the field of
cybernetics and he was one of the first
people who he was one of the founders of
of of computational science he was a big
deal
norbert winer and his his his his work
had
tremendous impact on all sorts of fields
and he was trying to figure out
uh how to generate autonomous
self-correcting systems
so let's say intelligence systems and
us among them because we're autonomous
self-correcting systems and so gray knew
about norbert weiner's work and he
integrated that with
isaac's work and then with all the
psychobiology and he came up with a
lovely
set of ideas that are extraordinarily
useful
and so here's one of them
we live inside we perceive this is part
of perceiving the world as a story
we perceive the world as a place
to go from one location to another
so you can imagine that we're on a
journey that's our life it's a journey
and
it might be a ten 10-minute journey it
might be a
15-minute journey it might be the
journey of a week it might be
the journey of a month or the journey of
a lifetime and
you know maybe what you would want is
that the journey of
a minute and 10 minutes and a week and a
month
and a year culminate into the journey of
a lifetime you know you could imagine
that you would want some continuity
across all that so that
that there was some what would integrity
to your existence
so that each part of what you were doing
was related in some intelligible way to
the whole
that would be that would be an ideal
when you think of someone as ha
as as being integrated right as having
character
something like that um that's really
what you mean is you mean that
all the parts of what they do fit
somehow into an integrated whole
and so that's kind of interesting to
know too because if you have a value
system that's well structured then
all the little things you do are part of
the big thing
that you're doing whatever that big
thing is
and you are doing that big thing okay so
so that's that's another thing to keep
in mind
now so you're looking at the world
you're a creature of action you have to
be a creature of action because you
have to act in order to live because if
you don't act
well then you fall apart and you're
overwhelmed by despair
and negative emotion and you starve to
death and you die and so
not acting not an option
so unless you willing to take the
consequences i just described so you
better look at the world as a place to
act
and so how do you act well
you're somewhere you should know where
you are by the way
that that's very helpful psychologically
you know
imagine you have a map you're in a car
and you don't know where you are
you're trying to get somewhere the map's
not helpful because you don't know where
you are
and so even if you know where you're
going but you don't know where you are
the map isn't useful and
the same applies the same really does
apply to your life
if you don't know where you are it's
very hard to map out where you're going
and well that has consequences for
emotion as well because going somewhere
is actually what activates the positive
emotion system that's what it's for
the positive emotion system is to
facilitate movement forward to a better
place
that's its function so that's so
interesting because it means that
if you're not moving forward to a better
place
then you don't have any positive emotion
and so that
and there's another conclusion that you
can derive from that too which is that
if you don't have a value system
you don't have any positive emotion
because the value system is what posits
that one thing is worth doing more than
another
and if one thing isn't worth doing more
than another
then you don't have any value any place
valuable to go
and if you don't have any place valuable
to go go then you don't have any
positive emotion
and so that's so when people are
criticizing hierarchies
which they do a lot especially
politically there shouldn't be
hierarchies it's like
really really there shouldn't be
hierarchy say
how is it that you propose to look at
the world
because you look at the thing that you
think is most important to look at at
that point
and if you couldn't you wouldn't even
know what to look at you know maybe
you've seen
i've seen videos youtube videos of
cameras that have been dropped from
space
accidentally um maybe it wasn't
accidentally it might have been part of
an advertising campaign for maybe
one of those you go things what do they
call those
what is it yeah gopro that's it
so they dropped one i think from like 30
miles up and it spun around all the way
down
and videotaped it's like pretty dull
because
why well because because it's not
pointed at anything it's not directed
towards anything
like it's a perfectly objective portrait
of reality
that's absolutely pointless right
because there's there's no
nothing is zeroing in on anything you
know and you even to organize your damn
vision
even to focus your eyes you have to have
a value harkey because you have to be
focusing on something that you think is
important
and if you think it's important it has
to be more important than other things
in fact it has to be more important than
everything else at that moment because
otherwise you wouldn't be focusing on it
and so there's no getting rid of
hierarchies not not unless you want to
disregulate your perceptual structures
entirely
and sacrifice your emotional stability
no more positive emotion
plenty of confusion though
and be immobilized and then also
sit there and do nothing and suffer and
die and so
let the idea that there's something
intrinsically wrong with hierarchies
that's
it's wrong it's wrong it's really deeply
wrong it's
deeply and stupidly wrong at multiple
levels
and so then the question becomes more um
appropriately well what should the
hierarchy be
and not whether or not there should be
one it's like and and you know it's not
like i'm not
cognizant of the negative consequences
of hierarchies
it's not like they're all positive you
know i mean no matter what hierarchy we
set up
to pursue what goal it doesn't matter
what the goal is
some people turn out to be better at
doing that and some people turn out to
be worse
and the people who turn out to be worse
pay a fairly heavy price for being worse
and so you set up a hierarchy there are
people and more people
at the bottom that are worse pay a
fairly heavy price
and so it's not like hierarchies are
without cost
and i would say to the degree that the
left end of the political spectrum
has a valid point their valid point is
pay some attention to the people at the
bottom of the hierarchies because it's a
rough place to be and
keep the hierarchies fair so that people
can move up and keep them
focused on their tasks so they're doing
useful things
and aren't corrupted by people who are
only seeking power
all of that fine no hierarchy
that's a bad idea that's a non-starter
okay so
now you're deciding to go somewhere and
it
it doesn't matter where it is small
scale journey or large scale journey
because a large-scale journey is
composed of
a multitude of small scale journeys so
i'll give i'll give you an example of
this i'm going to build up a moral
hierarchy for you from from the bottom
okay and and here here's one of the
things that's kind of cool about doing
this because
it actually solves to some degree the
mind body problem
if you do that and so if you're sitting
there thinking geez i wish that i could
solve the mind body problem tonight then
you know maybe tonight's your lucky
night because maybe that's what's
going to happen so um imagine that
imagine that you're going to do
something like prepare
dinner you might think that's a good
thing
so that's interesting so it's an action
but we'd also put a moral dimension on
it it's good to feed hungry people
yourself included maybe you do a good
job of making dinner that'd even be
better not only are you making dinner
but you're making a good dinner and so
that that makes making dinner an even
more impressive moral feat because you
could make some wretched
cold dismal massive glutinous
catastrophe and serve it with contempt
and hatred to the people that that are
around you you know
you could do that and it would still be
dinner but you know
it'd be it'd be a low quality it'd be a
low quality
and and all too common occurrence um
but let's say that you do it right you
know it's like you're going to put some
effort into it it's going to be
delicious that'd be nice it's going to
be nutritious it's going to be
attractive
and it's going to be served with the
proper attitude you know you're happy
that you have some food
that's kind of nice hasn't been all that
long that everybody had food
and certainly hasn't been all that long
that everybody had a vast variety of
high quality food and so a little
gratitude would be nice and
so so you got your so so even
so back to the back to the task at hand
you're you're going to make dinner so
the question is well what exactly
do you do to make dinner and it's kind
of an abstract idea to make dinner let's
go make dinner you can say that
abstractly but
when you actually go to make dinner it's
not abstract anymore
you go into the kitchen and you open the
refrigerator
and that that's not abstract right
that's not
mental it's physical you're interacting
with the world you grab the door handle
on the refrigerator
and you open it you don't really know
how you do that you know i mean i know
you know how to close your hand and move
your arm
but you don't know how you know how to
close your hand
and open the door your your mind that's
where your mind runs out
it knows how to operate your voluntary
musculature
but it doesn't know how so your mind
grounds out in your body
and and and and i'm going to make the
case that morality does that as well and
it's part of this
idea that the world is an
action-oriented place
you open the fridge you think hey
carrots
we're going to need some carrots so you
take the bag of carrots out of the
fridge and you put them on the counter
and you peel the carrots and again same
thing bit of expert behavior there you
know because you've peeled carrots
before and it's a bit deterministic
because you've learned how to do it
habitually and so you peel the carrots
and you take out the parts that aren't
so edible if you have any scents
and then you take out your knife and
maybe you have a nice
knife with a nice wide blade at the end
so you can chop up carrots it's kind of
fun to do that if you're good at it
because you can
you know make 100 slices in 20 or 30
seconds if you've practiced it and you
take your carrot and you go and then you
have
all these you don't have to make that
noise by the way but but but
you can if you want and then if if
you're good at it then all the carrots
are pretty much the same thickness and
that's kind of cool you got a little
expertise there and you got all the
carrots lined up and
maybe then you put them in some foil and
you add a little butter and some
i don't know cumin and a bit of pepper
and
make them into a foil packet this is
what we do in canada
you might do that you guys barbecue i've
heard and then you throw the things on
the barbecue and
and you wait till they're steam puffs up
the
foil and you think done and if you have
any sense at the same time you know
you're cooking the steak and
it's done at the same time in the
potatoes and it's all done at the same
time and it's caramelized nicely so it's
got a bit of sweetness and
you know you've got the right amount of
butter for the potatoes and you serve it
and
and that's that's good that's good and
it took you a long time to learn that
and there's a hierarchy there right so
the hierarchy is
the lowest part of the hierarchy is the
muscular movements say that you
you employ when you're slicing up the
carrots
there's nothing abstract about that and
then there's the
the sequencing of the carrots in the
foil and the placing them on the
on the uh on the grill and all of that
and that's
that's where the the the rubber hits the
road
and you think well hey i made a good
dinner and
then you might think well what's making
a good dinner a subset of
you might think well you know if you're
a good
friend good parent
maybe one of the things that you could
do is make a good dinner like it's not
the only thing
that i make a good dinner and so i'm a
good friend it's like no
but maybe that's one-fifth of it or a
tenth of it it's
it's some non-trivial proportion of it
necessary but not sufficient
is that right no no that's not right
it's not necessary
um anyways it's one of the things you
could do to be a good friend and then
you know if you have a friend maybe he
makes you a good dinner now and then and
there's some reciprocity there so
that's and so you're capable of engaging
in that reciprocity and that's another
thing that might make you a good friend
and
or a good parent let's say so let's say
there's 10 things like that at that
level that make you a good parent
it's like well what you can make a good
meal you can uh you can clean up the
kitchen
that's a good thing to be able to do you
can clean up the bathroom um
and there and the rest of the house um
so there's maybe five
you know how to clean well that's part
two of being a good parent
um you you get along with your partner
you you know how to negotiate with them
and and some of the things you negotiate
about are those lower level
tasks that you're going to engage in
it's like well
i made dinner maybe you could clean up
the kitchen and
you know there'd be some reciprocity
there and if you're a good
person which is getting a little higher
up in the value hierarchy
then you can engage in that kind of
negotiation
so but and and that is exactly what you
would be in gate
negotiating is those tasks and so well
so maybe you're the sort of partner that
can communicate with your partner and
maybe you're the sort of parent that can
bring their children into the kitchen
and
teach them the mechanical elements of
food preparation starting at the bottom
right i mean maybe you're not going to
give them the sharp
knife to begin with but you might get
them to set the table it's like
they're two and a half it's like table
needs to be set here's a spoon
kid take the spoon the kid can do that
he knows what a spoon is
you don't say um set the table for a
dinner party of 20
to a two and a half year old right
because they haven't got that level of
abstraction mastered
you say you see this yes
pat pat here's a spoon yes
can you say spoon spoon good good
take the spoon take it good
you know where the table is yes how
about if you go put the spoon on the
table
it's like yeah i can do that so the kid
wanders over and puts the spoon on the
table and
and then maybe comes back and looks at
you and they look at you to think is
well
did i get the spoon on the table right
did i did i do it right
that's one thing did i undertake the
action correctly
that's one thing and was it a good
action right did i do something that was
morally appropriate they're trying to
check both of those out at the same time
and you pat them on the head and you say
hey good job man you're growing up and
by that you also signify to them that
growing up is a good thing and that's
also important and then you say well
here's another spoon you're going to
encounter lots of spoons in your life
why don't you go put it on the table too
and so you know they put the spoons on
the table and then maybe you show them
how the spoons might be arranged and
then maybe you trust them with a fork
and then they can do the same thing and
then with the knife and you know a dull
butter knife sort of thing at least to
begin with and and with it
with the with the with the dishes and
you teach them
bottom up right reflex upward
you teach them the mechanics of
preparing something complex
and so they have all those micro skills
embedded in them so to speak and they're
part of their
their psychophysiological ability and at
some point with
a certain amount of training might take
three months four months six months
you can say set the table
and then the kid knows exactly what to
do and they don't know what to do until
they have all those micro routines
mastered and so that's kind of cool
because what it indicates is that the
the command the the macro command
set the table is only something that has
a meaning
when the micro processes that are
motoric
have already been mastered and that's a
really good way of thinking about how
you're constituted like you have a lot
of skills
things you can do with your body act
action-oriented skills and perceptual
skills and once you have them
as part of you then other people can
refer to them
and you understand each other and that's
partly how we understand each other is
that we
share a hierarchy of skill and
perception that's built from the bottom
up
to a very high level of abstraction and
also a very high level of isomorphism
meaning it's the same for everyone
so so so okay i'll explain that
momentarily here so now
we already established that you have to
do things and
i i'm going to elaborate on that claim a
little bit so you have to do things
and you have emotional systems that help
you decide
whether you're on the right path because
if you have to do things you're on a
path
and if you're going somewhere you better
be on the right path
and so then you need something to tell
you whether or not you're on the right
path
and that's what your emotions do your
positive emotion
and your negative emotion they're
orienting systems
that tell you whether you're on the
right path and the path is defined by
the goal
so you need a goal so that's the first
thing to think about
it's really really really really
important to think about this
if your life is not the way you want it
to be
it's possible that your goal is not what
it should be
and that's a fundamental religious
teaching by the way
i would say that might be the
fundamental religious teaching of
buddhism
right because the buddhists teach in
some sense that everything is maya or
illusion and and it's a complicated idea
but partly what it means is the way the
world
manifests itself to you is in large part
determined by your aim within the world
and so by switching aim you can switch
whether something is
positive or negative like let's say you
come home and you find your wife's
having an affair
it's like man you're you're not happy
you're one bitter
twisted angry person and you know you go
down to the bar and you have a few
drinks and you thought
god you know i really never liked her
and you think hey this is the best day
of my life my wife had an affair it's
like
i'm free i know this is a ridiculous
story but you get my point you know it's
like
you you could make a switch like that
you think well isn't it so strange it's
like half an hour ago
i was like bitter and twisted and angry
and resentful and anxious and
and frustrated and disappointed because
there was something i wanted
and i wasn't getting it and now all of a
sudden i've decided i didn't want that
and everything is switched around and so
that's
that's a that's a kind of a that's a
miracle that that can happen
and so in rule six you know i i the rule
is um
put your house in perfect order before
you criticize the world
well so what's the idea it's like well
if the world isn't
up to your standards let's say first of
all you might ask yourself about that to
begin with
it's like the world isn't up to your
standards
really that's and that's the world's
problem
somehow it's it's not more likely that
it's
given that you're talking about the
world here it's not more likely that
there's some chance that it's your
problem
and that if you put yourself right then
the world wouldn't appear to be a
problem and i mean it's a profound
question you know and
i'm not throwing that out cynically or
sarcastically i mean i've been
disenchanted with the world
a fair number of times personally i'm
including myself in
in the list of people who make that
error but you know
knowing that your emotional reactions
are dependent on your aim
and that that's actually technically
true does immediately open up the
question
hey man if things aren't laying
themselves in front of you
out in front of you the way that is
necessary for you to live a full
and engaged life and not be cynical and
bitter and twisted and cruel and
vengeful
and and disappointed in all of that it's
just
possible that you're not aiming at the
right thing
and man that is a question that is a
question worth asking
well it's the question people do ask
it's like well what's the purpose of
life
well it's the same question what should
i aim at those are the same questions
and you know if if what you're aiming at
is producing nothing but
unrequited misery for you and everyone
else and it's a downhill bloody spiral
into something
approximating hell then there is some
possibility
that you should think that perhaps your
aim is off
so and and i don't want to overplay my
hand on that either too because i know
perfectly well that
you know if you're suffering if you're
depressed if you're miserable
there might you might be you might just
it might be a consequence of really bad
luck
you know like people get sick and good
people get sick right everyone knows
that you know good people they get sick
and they die and so you can't say well
if you're miserable
and sick it's because there's something
you know bad about you
because then that would be the case for
everyone
always whenever they get ill and you
could just blame the old people it's
like well it's seriously right that
you're sick because you're a bad person
it happens a lot actually with ill
people you know and it's an unfortunate
thing
so i know there's an element of chance
to all this and i don't want to
downplay that you know we are
dust in the wind to use a terrible
cliche from a 70s rock song
um we're blowing hither and thither by
events that are somewhat beyond our
control but that's still not the point
the point is that to a large degree you
can determine the manner in which the
world manifests itself to you
by changing your aim and so then that
opens up that opens up the entire
domain of philosophy you think what good
is philosophy and people think that all
the time what good is philosophy it's
like
hey philosophy is about value well what
use is value
well value determines your aim well who
cares what your aim is
well your aim determines the manner in
which the world
lays itself out to you emotionally
well who cares about that no one says
that
the argument stops there because no one
especially no one who's been seriously
hurt
or seriously depressed like in pain no
one ever says
oh well who cares about that because if
you can say that about your pain
all that means is you actually haven't
been in pain
because if you're in enough pain you
will not say that that's for sure
so you need to know what to aim at so
now you aim at something you've got a
goal and then
you see that you're making progress
towards the goal
that's a good thing that makes you
happy it actually technically
there's a system dopamine system
neurochemical system
same system by the way that cocaine and
methamphetamine and
and opiates activate which is why people
like to take those drugs
and it tells you that you're
you're moving forward in the manner that
you should be according to the
dictates of your plan doesn't
necessarily tell you whether you have a
good plan
that's a more complicated problem
because who knows if you have a good
plan
but but one thing that you could know is
that a plan
is better than no plan that's a really
useful thing to know especially if
you're kind of drifting
it's like well i'm going to find myself
it's like no
just pick something and and move towards
it
and as you move towards it you're going
to succeed and fail
specifically and then you're going to
learn something about success
specifically and you're going to learn
something about failure
specifically and then you can learn what
you use
to fix your plan so so a stupid plan is
way better than no plan and
you're likely to have a stupid plan or
at least to be able to make one so
that's good news for everybody you can
make a stupid plan and so i would
say make a stupid plan and then
implement it not any stupider than it
has to be you know you could think about
it a little bit
but then implement it and have your
successes and failures along the way
and learn from them and then you can rig
you can rejig the goal
you can move the target that's that's
fine that's that's that's part of the
game it doesn't have to be fixed
it's a movable target and maybe what
you're trying to do is to move the
target to an
ever better place so so you're moving
towards a target and at the same time
you're moving the target
right and and and you're trying to move
the target towards something like an
ultimate ideal you're trying to find out
what that ultimate ideal is
and part of the way you figure that out
is by moving towards a target
and by learning about success and
failure along the way because then you
can inform yourself with regards to what
might constitute a reasonable aim
and so that's the reason to go out in
the world and like make some mistakes
you know
and then you're going to and so it's
okay because
it's okay to make the mistakes it's not
so okay not to learn from them
because then you make the mistakes again
that seems pointless
and so you're moving towards wherever
you're going and it's working
and so you get some positive emotion you
get some
motivation from this dopaminergic system
that adds
zest to life it adds interest and
engagement and meaning to life it
pulls you into life and so and that's
worth thinking about
i would say because if you think about
it you know you have
might wonder about whether or not you
should be engaged in life
and then if all of a sudden you're doing
something and because you're doing it
you get engaged in life
then it seems like that might be the
very
definition of a good thing it's evidence
the engagement is evidence that you're
actually doing a good thing a worthwhile
thing
in life with all its suffering and
misery and brutality
it's like you've got a pathway you've
got an aim you're moving forward you're
engaged
excellent your nervous system very deep
down
this dopaminergic system it's associated
with a part of the brain called the
hypothalamus
it's a really really old part of the
brain
it's not some new thing that popped up
like 15 000 years ago
it's ancient it's there to orient you in
the world it's it's part of the instinct
for meaning that i talked about in
chapter
i think it's chapter seven do what is
meaningful and not what is expedient
it's a deep deep instinct and
way down in way down in your
psychophysiological structure not as far
down as the serotonin system but
like next level up and so if it's saying
hey man you're on the right track it's
like that's worth
noticing it's worth noticing now you can
criticize it out of existence you can
question your your aim continually it's
one of the
what would you call it dangers of our
capacity to abstract but
you know if you're a smart person who
doubts you also might be smart enough
now and then to
doubt your doubt and just to notice
and to pay attention and something i
explain to my clinical clients and my
students often it's like
if you're trying to put your life
together watch yourself for a couple of
weeks
like you don't know who you are because
if your life isn't together you don't
know who you are
so just watch yourself like you don't
know who you are and notice
now and then if you're engaged in
something
you know and you kind of have to wake up
because if you're engaged in it you
don't quite notice right because you're
engaged in it
but afterwards you might think oh i just
spent an hour
and i didn't notice that it was an hour
i was
in it that's good you're in the right
place at the right time doing the right
thing there's something about that
that's right
and maybe like you're not in good shape
and that happened to you like 15 minutes
once in two weeks it's like that's
pretty dismal and the rest of the time
it was wretched it's like okay fine well
maybe in the next two weeks you can see
if you can do it for half an hour
and then maybe for 45 minutes and then
maybe for an hour right you can start
practicing
being in that place that's a very useful
thing to learn it's like oh look i'm
interested in what i'm doing i'm engaged
in it
now how did i get here where am i
exactly and how did i get here
and how could i stay here how could i be
here more often
those are all questions you have to ask
yourself well that's the beginning of
philosophy as well
and you think well why bother and the
answer is well do you want to be engaged
in your life
well why would you well
it's positive it's analgesic it fights
off pain
it quells anxiety it gives you purpose
it's good for you practically speaking
generally speaking if you have an aim
and you're moving forward you're moving
forward to something that's
psychologically valuable but also
practically valuable if it's really a
good aim
also it's good for you now tomorrow the
next day the next month
because you're smart enough to generally
smart enough
to calibrate yourself so that things
that are really bad for
you don't have that engaging quality now
it's not perfect especially if you've
messed yourself up psychologically by
lying to yourself
in all sorts of different ways but it's
still not a bad orienting system
and then the other thing you can also
notice is well when are you doing things
that make you feel really awful
by your own standards it's like oh look
i just did something had some
interaction with someone and now i feel
awful
it's like well maybe you could not do
that
whatever it was you might have to think
it through
what were the routines that constituted
that ill-advised set of actions
and maybe you're gonna have to think
really deeply about it you know because
god only knows
how much of your personality structure
is involved in that
error but if it made you wretched it
made you feel like life wasn't worth
living then
that might be a hint that that wasn't a
good thing to do and so then maybe you
could start doing more of the things
that make you engaged
and less of the things that make you
hate life
and that's worthy that's worthy of
practice
let's say you might think about that as
a it's a fundamental ethical requirement
or i would say it's a fundamental form
of religious meditation
that's a better way of thinking about it
and so then you're on the path that's
the straight and narrow path it's like
i'm moving forward i've got name i'm
moving forward
as i move forward i'm engaged it's
bloody well worth
walking down this pathway and you know
on the left of me is
terror and horror and hell and pain and
i'm avoiding that
and to the right of me perhaps is ego
and arrogance and the things that can
get out of control
with regards to positive emotion but
i've got that balance right i'm on the
right pathway
okay now we think about what might
constitute the right pathway
well um i can tell you a pathway that
works
for me to some degree so this is a value
structure that's characteristic of
me of things i do
i type because i write and so that's
pure action right i type letters i type
words
i type phrases i type sentences i type
paragraphs
i type chapters i write books
and then people and then i talk about
the books and people read the books and
the reason that they can understand the
books is because
we're a lot the same you know like
there's a lot of things that have to be
the
same about you and me before i can write
a book that you can read
and i have to be able to take them for
granted and so
the reason i'm telling you that is
because there's an important
relationship between my hierarchy of
values
and your hierarchy of values if we're
going to be able to communicate and if
we're going to be able to occupy the
same place at the same time
you know so if i'm writing a book like
12 rules for life and it
has a discussion about what constitutes
the good in it
then i have to start with the
presupposition that
we share some fundamental intuition
about what constitutes the good or
my words will fall on deaf ears
okay and it's partly because
and then and this is this is maybe the
relationship between
the social world and the psychological
world that i wanted to talk about
as i build up my hierarchy of skill and
ability
perception and emotional regulation you
know from
slicing carrots upwards you know i'm a
i'm a good cook i'm a good parent
maybe i'm a good man maybe i'm a good
person you know
and all of those cover a broader and
broader range of abstractions and
abilities
there has to be a relationship between
that and what other people think
you know because look if you're
your kid you teach your kid to set the
table and then he goes to someone else's
house and sets the table and he gets a
swat
it's like well what's the consequence of
that
well the consequence of that is that the
kid is going to be unhappy
well why well it's because the kid did a
lot of work
building up all those separate skills to
undertake that complex activity and it
really is a complex activity you don't
have a robot at home that sets the table
you know you have a cell phone and it's
smart but it can't set the damn
table it's complicated to do that sort
of thing and so your kid
had built this complicated neurological
structure as a consequence of reward
primarily because reward helps build
neurological structures
built this whole structure and now what
he's hoping is that all the work that
went into building that structure
is something that other people will
appreciate as well
so that's where you need the isomorphism
between
the intra-psychic structure the
psychological structure and the social
structure
which is why we have to have a shared
social reality
this is partly why i think the
postmodernists went off the rails so
badly with their insistence that the
world was only language
it's like it is in some sense very
important that
you construe the world the same way i do
even though there's a very
wide range of ways of construing the
world we come to some negotiated
agreement about
what's good and what isn't so that when
i do things that i think
are good you also think they're good so
that i get rewarded for my good behavior
and i get
let's say punished for my bad behavior
because that's often a relief as well by
the way
and so we have to have our own
internal structure of values that we're
pursuing
because otherwise we don't have any
meaning in our life and that's no damn
good
and then it has to be nested inside a
shared
structure of values that's similar so
that when we act out what we
have learned to be good we're treated by
the world as if that's good
and then we have peace that's the
definition of that's a definition of a
functioning political system we've
we've we've organized a moral game a
very complex one
and then we master it through reciprocal
interaction with one another
we internalize it so that it regulates
our emotions then we act it out in the
world and if there's a concordance
between the way we acted out and the way
the world responds
then we're okay because there's nothing
more
disturbing to you than to act out a high
order moral good
let's say you're working really hard at
your job for example and you're hoping
for a promotion
and let's say you deserve a promotion by
all reasonable standards
and then you don't get one you know it's
it's taken it's given to i don't know
given to the bosses mistress or some
damn thing or you know
it's given to someone who doesn't
deserve it by the canonical rules of the
moral game
and all it does is devastate you and the
reason that it devastates you is because
it disrupts the
relationship between the internal moral
hierarchy that you've built
and the collective hierarchy and
everything you have is staked on
maintaining that isomorphism you know
and it's the same even in
in in into intimate relationships you
know if you do something
good for your your wife or your husband
you know you go out of the way
maybe to make a nice meal and they come
home and they punish you
arbitrarily for some tiny fault maybe
with the dinner
it's very disheartening and the reason
is it
it it violates your faith first of all
in your own
intra-psychic hierarchy second in the
structure of the social hierarchy and
third in the match
between them and it's the match between
them that's really important we do not
like
mismatch between what we expect
especially in terms of
reward especially when we've really
worked at it and and what we're
delivered
right and so that that's partly how we
it's partly a complicated
explanation of how we regulate our
emotions you know we regulate them by
aiming
that's important we we regulate them by
walking the straight narrow path
but then we also regulate them by being
fortunate enough to be in a situation
where if we walk the straight and narrow
path
properly then other people respond
positively to us
and then you have this lovely harmony
and it's a right way of thinking about
it it's a musical way of thinking about
it
there's you composed of this very
unbelievably complex
nested set of patterns beautiful
patterns that you spent forever working
on
and then they're nested inside a social
structure that's also
patterned in the same way and those are
working harmoniously together like a
dance
and that's perfect it's it's it's it's
the it's the meeting of the individual
with society
and it's it's the secret to harmonious
emotional regulation and and more into
cooperation and and
to proper competition and to and to and
to movement forward practically in the
world
all of that and so okay well i'll i'll
close with
just a description of what a hierarchy
might look like um
and and a brief description of of how it
is that you calculate when you make
a major mistake so my hierarchy would be
something like this
i type letters i type words phrases
sentences
paragraphs i sequence the paragraphs i
make chapters
i write books it's all coherently laid
out towards some higher order aim
all of that and the aim is as far as i'm
concerned
to share my clinical knowledge and to
educate people and that makes sense
because i'm a clinician and a researcher
and a professor and so if i was going to
do that i've decided i'm going to do
that so
that's what i'm doing and hopefully
that's a good thing and
hopefully people respond to it as if
it's a good thing because then
that's a good thing for me and it's a
good thing for them and so that seems to
be like the very definition of a good
thing
and i'm trying to set things straight
right
i'm trying to set myself straight by
writing carefully
i'm trying to set the culture straight
by saying what i believe to be
the case i'm trying to set other
individuals straighter by communicating
with them
i'm trying to ensure that we can live
more harmoniously
in our culture and in the world and you
think well those are
good things to have at the outermost
reaches of your value
hierarchy you know my friend of mine was
talking to me about bricklayers the
other day and he's
trying to restructure a major company at
the moment and we were talking about how
to motivate people he said well let's
say you're a bricklayer it's like you
know
it's one damn brick after another how
are you going to be excited about that
well let's say you're a medieval
bricklayer
right and it's it's 1500 and you're
working in
you're working in one of the great uh
you're
working in one of the great early
renaissance cities in europe
and it isn't a wall you're building it's
a cathedral
it's going to take 350 years and why are
you doing that well it's for the
ultimate glory of god whatever that
means and so
you're not putting one brick down after
another
it's like you're involved in this
unbelievably complicated moral structure
that stretches really stretches all the
way up to heaven
itself so to speak and each of your
minor actions you know your local
actions
is imbued with the spirit of that entire
moral structure
well that's a philosophy it's like well
do you have a meaning in life
what's the meaning of life well
hopefully it isn't just unrequited
suffering and malevolence we could
dispense with that as much as possible
that might be a good start
but then to aim high well that seems to
be reasonable
to aim as high as you can and we've laid
out things that could be aimed at
you could constrain yourself you know
there are things you're not doing
and things that you shouldn't be doing
you stop doing the things that you
shouldn't be doing
and start doing the things you should be
doing that's a good start
wake up enough so that you can set the
structures around you right
it's your moral obligation as a citizen
your responsibility and your
divine duty i would say from our
cultural perspective because
in the west everyone is regarded as a
sovereign individual
the fate the fate of the state
a sovereign individual on whose
shoulders
rests the fate and the health of the
state
right that's the fundamental
presupposition otherwise
why do you get to vote to just to make a
mistake
well no that's not it you're supposed to
be awake so that the
ship of state continues to move forward
in the appropriate direction and somehow
we've
decided that's up to you why
well because we've also decided hey man
you can do it and not only that no one
else can
and so that's something to know and
might be something to take seriously
it's like who knows what the hell you'd
be if you got your act together
and i think you would be like you'd be a
force to contend with you know
you'd have constrained the malevolence
of in your own soul
and you'd have started to take advantage
of the potential that's around you and
to build yourself out of that potential
into god only knows what
you know and then and then maybe with
that wisdom you can set
the structures around you in order at
least more in order than they are
or maybe to disintegrate them a bit when
they need it and to restructure them so
they're even better than they are
and you can push back nature and it's in
its horrible form and
invite it forward in its positive form
and make things better for you and
for your family and for your community
and you can approach the unknown itself
and you can explore that the potential
that's out there
and you can bring back the treasure
that's part of the unknown potential
and you can distribute that and that is
what you can do
and then not only that's what you need
to do because you need to have
a meaning in your life a name a value
structure that's of
sufficient potency and
magnitude to justify the limitations and
the trouble that life constitutes right
it's not
this is no trivial business that we're
involved in right
we're all in this up to our necks
literally it's a
it's a mortal game you're all in
and and there's and and and to play it
wrong is is
is to risk suffering in hell and and i'm
not talking about
afterlife i'm not talking about
something metaphysical you can generate
plenty of hell
right here around you plenty an
unlimited amount
and so you can move towards that
direction or you can move towards a
positive direction
and you can orient yourself and you know
you can know you can learn
this is why the postmodernists are so
incorrect it's like look
you need a name you need a name
you cannot organize the way you look at
the world without a name
it's not optional and then the question
is well
what should the aim be well
not to radically increase the amount of
misery and suffering that you experience
in everyone else i mean maybe you want
to go that route but
and people do but i think they only do
when they become bitter
and they give up you know they and they
make mistakes they know they're making
right it's it's conscious decision to go
down that route
it's not like they think that's okay to
begin with their aim's wrong
it's like straighten out your aim so
there's an old idea this idea of sin sin
is a word that was derived from a greek
word hamartia
and hamartia is an archery term and it
means to miss
the target and so you think well how can
you miss the target
well you have no weapon
well then you miss the target you
you have no target you have no aim well
then
then you miss the target you don't pick
up your bow
well then you miss the target you don't
draw it back then you miss the target
you don't practice and and miss many
times right
because you have to do that to develop
the skill to hit the target
so you're not willing to take the risk
to miss you you do none of that
and so you miss the target and that's
the sin
and then you miss your life and then
what happens around you is that
well there's far more hell than there
has to be and there's much less heaven
than there could be
and it's on you and that's part of your
what would you say your divine value
let's say
that that sets you aside along with
everyone else as
as something someone some being that
even the law
itself has to respect intrinsically and
it's marked out in our culture by
the sovereignty that you possess and the
notion that
there's something in you that's made in
the image of god
something that can confront the unknown
and to create
habitable order out of chaos and
potential and to do that properly
and that's all true as far as i can tell
and it's all necessary to know it's
coded in the deepest stories
that are at the base of our culture and
we're we're in danger of not
understanding them and not believing
them and it's a big mistake
because they're heavy and profound
and weighty and fundamental
and necessary because you have to stand
on something that's solid
or everything is sand and you you fall
in
and you're done and so is everything
around you
well so that's what was the name of the
talk
what was the name of the talk i don't
even remember what the hell i titled it
now
part of it is yes the relationship
between your internal psychological
structure and the social world
that's what's part of it and then the
manner by which you estimate magnitude
of error i suppose that's the last thing
i should say
you have a value hierarchy and we
already described what that is
ranging from the trivial motor actions
that you undertake to the highest order
aims what makes you upset
your determination of how far up in the
hierarchy
the error you have made has disrupted
things
you know so you tell your kid
you didn't put that spoon on the table
quite right and they're a little upset
you know but it's
whatever you twist the spoon it's fixed
or you say you know you're a rotten kid
and you've always been a rotten kid and
i don't see that there's much hope for
you in the future
it's like well well people do that when
they argue with people they love and
they do that quite a bit
it's like you're taking them out at the
highest level of their value hierarchy
right
and that makes people really upset and
the reason for that is well it wipes up
their whole map
and so there's also a relationship this
is an interesting thing to know
between how upset you get emotionally
and how important it is how important
the thing that you're pursuing is that's
being criticized
and it's oh and with a practical note
you know if you're arguing with someone
here's something you can think about you
want them to change their behavior
the first thing you want to do is you
want to sort of pat them on the head
and say
you weren't horrible all the time in the
past and you're not horrible all the
time now and you probably won't be
horrible all the time
in the future so we'll just get that out
of the way
but there's this small thing that you do
that could use a little improvement and
here's
how you can improve it and i would be
satisfied and happy with that
if you tried it would you be willing to
and then they improve incrementally and
over time
maybe if you're very careful with such
things and you don't do them too often
and you also allow the other person to
do that to you
as well then you get incremental
improvements without
taking chopping people off at the knees
so to speak when you're criticizing the
way that they're behaving
all right well how to conclude all that
you can't look at the world without a
name
literally you can't even perceive it you
cannot
regulate your emotions without a name
the better your aim the more precise
your aim
the more elevated your aim you remember
in in pinocchio when when gepetto wants
to turn pinocchio into a real boy
he wishes on a star it's a strange thing
eh
but everybody just accepts it it's like
well yeah if you've got a puppet
you just made a puppet and you want to
turn it into a boy the logical thing to
do is open the window and wish on a star
everyone knows that it's like
none of that makes the least bit of
sense obviously
except metaphorically but we do
understand it because we can watch that
and it makes sense it's
something magical about it and there is
something magical about it
because the truth of the matter is is
that if you want to transform
something that's nothing but a wooden
headed puppet into something that's a
fully functional
autonomous moral autonomous individual
then what you do is you elevate your
eyes above the horizon to the highest
point of light that you can perceive
and you aim at that and that works
and that works for you and it works for
your partner and it works for your
children
and it works for the world thank you
very much
there was one here i thought was quite
oh who would wear when in a bare knuckle
brawl between
you ben shapiro and justin trudeau
well ben's a malevolent little creature
so
[Laughter]
so he might have some dirty tricks up
his sleeve but he doesn't
he doesn't have much of a reach on him
um
trudeau trudeau
he can box so he
he'd probably get me on technical skills
and i'm i'm quite a bit older but
i i think i'd get up a lot of times
so well hopefully it won't come to that
but
but i tell you there is part of me that
that thinks it would be interesting
all right all right so and there was 137
of you who thought that one was
worth discussing so that's good so
is the sole purpose of religious ideas
to propagate the species
no it's not the sole purpose
um we discussed that a lot today
the sole purpose of religious ideas the
sole purpose
first of all the questioner assumes that
there is a sole purpose and
and i don't i don't think that that's
accurate so you want to be careful about
reducing something complex to a single
explanation that's generally the purview
of
ideologues right they have one idea and
it just covers the world
and the world is a little bit too
complex more too complicated to be
covered by
by one one idea unfortunately
um the purpose of religious ideas as far
as i could tell is to remind us who we
are
you know we don't live that long right
and and we're really complicated
and it's not easy to learn how to be a
person you know i mean it takes you like
40 years before you can learn to be a
person
enough so that you can get out of your
mother's basement
so it's hard that's half your life
before
well maybe not 40 but but certainly
sometimes
um it takes a long time to learn how to
be a human being and
and we're very very complicated we're
we're way more complicated than we can
understand
you know and we've been watching each
other for a long time watching ourselves
telling stories about ourselves
trying to draw some wisdom from our self
observations
to teach to our children and to our
grandchildren and so forth and
we've codified them in all sorts of
strange ways in these
memorable stories fairy tales and myths
and religious stories all of those
things
and what are they there for
they're there to remind us who we are
because we need
to know who we are and you know we
talked about that a little bit tonight i
i believe the the notion that i i
believe the
most important idea that's ever
being generated is the the idea that
men and women are made in the image of
god
i think that a culture that doesn't that
isn't predicated on that belief
knowingly or unknowingly and better
knowingly is
doomed to absolute catastrophe
because there's no reason to assume that
there isn't something about
us that's of transcendent
value i mean
if if for no other reason than the fact
of our consciousness you know like here
we are we're aware
of of what there is and it isn't even
obvious
that there could be what there is if
there wasn't
something that's aware of it and so our
very awareness
is plays an integral role in the fact of
being itself you know and metaphysics
aside it's hard to see that anything
could be more
vital than that more important than that
and then it isn't only that we
apprehend reality you know and and
therefore give it
give it shape merely by our perceptions
it's also clearly the case
that we partake in its shaping
and and and we call ourselves on that
you know you you know you know that you
feel guilty and ashamed when
you're not doing what you could be doing
when you're not living up to your
potential
when you're not making the most of
what's offered to you
you understand at a very deep level that
you're
that you're that you're what would you
you're breaking there's no other way of
saying it you're breaking a divine
commandment
you're offered this unbelievably rich
possibility and it's there for you to
grapple with and and you say well i
don't believe
in such things that in in the divinity
of of humanity or in divinity itself
or in the divine for that matter but you
you can't
fool yourself with that kind of
argumentation it doesn't stop you from
feeling
guilty and ashamed and worthless and
disappointed and frustrated and angry
and vengeful at the fact that you're
wasting your life
and you're noticing it and that you're
making yourself
much less than you could be and that
you're making things around you
worse for everyone else and like
perhaps there's a psychopath or two in
the audience
who just doesn't give a damn and who is
focused only on instantaneous
gratification
for their most primordial impulses
this moment right but it's not a
sustainable mode of being
and it's very rare and so
the purpose of religious ideas is to
wake us up
it's to remind us who we are right it's
to remind us that we're
imbued with with a spirit
that can be best described in some sense
as a mortal
it's it's the spirit that allows all of
us to be conscious
that we all participate in
simultaneously that
gives rise to the world and shapes it
and then to alert us to
the vital importance of the
responsibility that goes along with that
because i do believe that we shape the
world
we move it towards heaven or we move it
towards hell
and we do that with every conscious
decision we make
and it moves in the direction
that we determine and so that's what
religious stories are there to
remind us of
fifty percent of queensland queensland
police are now required to be women
as a bloke applying how do i speak
intelligently and effectively into this
situation
um what percentage of queensland police
are now currently women is it
like 20 or 10 percent or does anybody
know is it a low percentage
it's it's what it's five okay so this
basically means that as a bloke applying
you don't have a hope in hell
right which is why uh 200 people thought
this was an important question
well as far as i'm concerned it's like
what the hell are you sitting around for
it's time for some political action
there's no excuse for this whatsoever
there's no excuse whatsoever for
equality
for equality of outcome measures
they're ideological to the core and
they're very oddly applied
it's like what percentage of women are
bricklayers i know i talked about
bricklayers already tonight but
it's a good example i i went on the u.s
if you go on on
on this this statistical site that's
that's operated by the us government
you can look at uh occupations by gender
and it's an interesting thing to do um
here's an interesting thing
you know the most common occupation for
women back in the 1950s was secretary
you know what the most common occupation
for women is now
it's secretary they don't call them
secretaries now that
it's usually executive assistant or
something like that and that may
indicate some elevation genuine
elevation and status but fundamentally
the the the most common occupation
hasn't changed in
what what's that 70 years so that's
pretty interesting
brick layers 99.9 of bricklayers
are men okay so and and then
it's the same for like heavy duty uh
construction equipment operators and
um people who are working with heavy
machinery tend to be men
people who are building things uh
especially outside tend to be men
overwhelmingly so um
far more even than engineers there's a
fair number of female engineers
it's like well what are we gonna do here
it's like we're gonna enforce
gender equality of outcome across the
board sexy quality of outcome across the
board
is that the theory and how are we going
to do that
exactly or are we going to just do it
hit and miss it's like oh well it's
policeman this year
well how about bricklayers it's like
what why don't we pass a law like
tomorrow
that now 50 of bricklayers have to be
women
it doesn't bloody well matter if the
women want to be bricklayers how it has
that's irrelevant who says anything
about want
it's like the only reason that women
don't want to be bricklayers is because
they've
internalized their misogyny
right well that that's the standard
answer
for that sort of gender inequality and
like is and where is it going to stop
so i i think i've thought for a long
time that the left can go too far
and i i think that if you don't think
that the left can go too far then
your head is so far stuck down in the
sand that
you're that i need an ending for that
metaphor i was thinking about
something far ruder and just made it
polite um
anyways i guess that's the ending to it
um obviously the left can go too far
the 20th century is a testament to that
venezuela is a testament to that
okay so when does the left go too far
because the left isn't
particularly interested in answering
that question and i would say the left
goes too far when they insist
upon equality of outcome legislation
now equality of opportunity is a
different thing because i think that if
you have any sense
imagine just imagine that you're just
greedy you know and self-centered
and and that you want the most for you
so we won't be too optimistic about your
motivations
and i don't think that most people are
like that by the way i think that
people are by and large pretty good at
reciprocal interactions
and they do like to have you know nice
things for themselves but they're often
hard on themselves
but they're they care about the people
they love and they care about their
families and
they're pretty good at reciprocal
interaction with other people too so i
don't think we are just
innately selfish to the core it
it doesn't work but let's assume you are
for a moment
well and then let's assume that you know
there's a bunch of things you don't know
how to do and
there's some people out there who have
some talent that might be able to do
them and if they
did them then you'd get to benefit you
know like you don't know how to make an
iphone
well some of you might but not the whole
thing but you know
some people know how to make an iphone
and you get to have one and so
stopping someone who could make an
iphone
from making one for some arbitrary
reason because of their sex or their
ethnicity or their race just seems
completely
counterproductive and it's pretty
obvious if you look around the world
and you look at countries that are
developing economically
here's one good indicator you know the
countries
that have um there's a very
high there's a very powerful
relationship between
the rights granted to women and the
economic
viability of a given country it's very
tightly associated
so that's quite cool because it seems to
indicate well maybe
openness to the participation of women
in in traditional societies
is also an indicator of openness to the
new you know to the novel
and so that's a good predictor of of
economic success or maybe it's that
women have 50 percent of the talent and
we could use the damn talent so
how about we invite them into play too
that seems perfectly reasonable and the
same goes for
as i said for ethnicity and and for race
and so i think you have to be a damn
fool not to
open up the hierarchies to those who are
competent
right to the maximal possible degree and
that it's an error not to do that
but to insist that the outcome is the
same it's like
it's so it's it's vile
as far as i'm concerned for a variety of
reasons the first reason is
there's no indication that any attempt
to do that in the 20th century
ended up in any other manner than
catastrophe
so that's the first thing the second
thing is
think it through think it through
it's like okay
50 of every occupation has to be
men and women okay you're really willing
to do that are you
and we could start with bricklayers it's
like how are you going to do that
you're going to start forcing girls when
they're like 13
to learn to lay bricks
and and how are you going to force them
to do that because maybe they're not
interested i i can tell you something
that's quite interesting about
the stem fields in women so um
as societies become more egalitarian
so their equality of opportunity
legislation
is more widespread and arguably more
effective
and so that would be in countries like
australia but more particularly in
countries like the scandinavian
countries because they've taken it
farther than anywhere else
fewer women go into the stem fields
fewer
not more and so if you rank order
countries by
how free women are there's a
negative relationship with how probable
it is that they'll go into
science technology engineering and
mathematics fields
now and and the evidence for that is
very very strong by the way this isn't
just a few casual studies
these are large-scale international
studies with tens of thousands of
participants
replicated multiple times by
researchers who did not expect to find
that
nor want it so it's reliable
okay so why well there's a bunch of
different theories one is that
um the average iq of men and women is
the same
and that's quite clear but the male
curve is flatter than the female curve
and that's the
what they call that the enhanced male
variability hypothesis which is
almost now become impossible to publish
on because it's politically incorrect
and what it suggests is that there are
more men at the very upper end of the
intelligence distribution
and more men at the very lower end and
that explains some things like why there
are far more boys for example who have
learning disabilities than there are
girls
and there's some evidence that men are
more neurologically vulnerable than
women because they're more
specialized neurologically and the
advantage to that is
this enhanced variability but the
disadvantage is the specialization makes
them less robust and resilient
neurologically
be that as it may that's one possibility
and i think there's a fair bit of
evidence for that
and and it's often the case that
differences at the extreme even if there
aren't differences in the middle
differences at the extreme actually make
a big difference
you know because like let's say you're
going to be an engineer maybe one person
in 100 is an engineer
and you have to be really interested in
gadgets to be an engineer
you know you have to be more interested
in 99 out of 100 people to be an
engineer
and there's not that many people that
are like that and most of them
happen to be men now people have
criticized the
male variability hypothesis because
they've looked at the performance of
girls
in mathematics in junior high school and
it turns out that
girls do pretty much as well as boys do
in mathematics in high school in junior
high
at the upper end and so those would be
the people you'd expect to go into the
stem fields right because they have the
what would you call they have the
intellectual ability for it
but what you see is that the women who
have high mathematical ability
also tend to have high verbal ability
whereas the men that have high
mathematical ability tend to have
less high verbal ability and so one of
the things that implies is that the
women who have high mathematical ability
have more vocational choice
and so they're statistically less likely
to go into the stem fields
so that's kind of an interesting no one
expected that so that's kind of an
interesting
observation and then there's another
observation too that's that's also
extraordinarily germane there's a
variety of ways of
looking at the psychological differences
and similarities between men and women
and the first thing that you might
want to know is that men and women are
more similar than they are different on
all the personality dimensions so the
overlap is quite strong
the biggest differences are there's five
personality dimensions
i mentioned them extroversion
neuroticism
uh agreeableness conscientiousness and
openness
the biggest differences are in
neuroticism
women are higher in negative emotion and
that kicks in at puberty because
it's not the case for boys and girls and
their
higher in agreeableness which is partly
why there are far more men in prison
which is another thing we might think
about is like what what is that
is that gender discrimination precisely
i'm bloody well dead serious about this
i went to a nato conference
25 years ago and there were a group of
female scientists there
who claimed that the psychiatric
diagnostic criteria for childhood
conduct disorder
should be re-vamped because there were
far more boys diagnosed with childhood
conduct disorder than there were girls
and that's the precursor by the way to
adult anti-social personality disorder
or to criminality and the way that you
equate it by sex if you want to do that
is you get rid of the violence so one of
the criteria for childhood conduct
disorder is
kicking hitting biting and stealing like
criminal behavior if you take that out
of the diagnostic criteria
then you get the same number of boys and
girls and that's what they were
advocating for
25 years ago and i thought you people
are completely out of your bloody minds
because the only reason that we ever
came up with the diagnosis for childhood
conduct disorder
was because we were worried that the
violent kids would become violent
adolescents and that they would become
violent
adults which is exactly what happens by
the way because
aggressive behavior is unbelievably
stable and difficult to alter
but they were perfectly willing to
gerrymander the diagnostic criteria
so that the sex difference disappeared
even though that would completely
invalidate the utility of the diagnosis
and their and their and their
fundamental claim was
um the reason that there were more men
in prison
than women was because um
it was a form of it was a form of
arbitrary prejudice
and that this is absolutely insane
so you know it is the case if you look
at domestic violence statistics by the
way women hit men more than men hit
women
just so you know um it actually doesn't
matter
mostly not that it's pleasant that isn't
what i'm saying is that men are a lot
stronger than women
they have a lot more powerful upper
bodies and so when when
men hit women the the consequences tend
to be very dire and when women hit men
well they're less dire and i'm not
saying that it's okay
but i but i am pointing out that you
know this this does happen
it's not the point the point is that you
know we're concerned about criminality
because we don't want violent people
attacking other people
in the streets disrupting the harmony of
society and generally
corrupting the integrity of the state
and so we put them in prison
and most of them are men it's like 10 to
15 to 1 and it's like that worldwide
okay what we're gonna 50
are now going to be women
so seriously look if the if the if this
if the theory is the only goddamn
difference between men and women
is a consequence of the oppressive
social structure that cuts both ways
and what that means is that if 85 or 90
of the people who are in prison are male
then the prison system is
unbelievably prejudiced against men
so we're going to act on that and how
that's easy
we lower the standards of criminal
behavior for women
until we equate the number of men and
women who are imprisoned
look that's what you're going to
yeah you know you think that's funny
that's what happens in the military
especially at the higher ends you know
in in in the operations like navy seals
or the places where there's tremendous
emphasis on physical readiness
the only way you can equate by gender
is to reduce the performance criteria
that the women have to attain
so if you can do it there then why the
hell can't you do it for criminality
if the goal is equality of outcome where
are you going to stop
and then that's easy if the goal is
equality of outcome
you stop when the outcomes are equal
and not just the desirable outcomes you
know you hear about the fact that
well if you look at the c-suites of
major corporations that
a majority of the people are men it's
like well the first thing i think about
that is
well what the hell's your point it's
like that's hardly anyone right
99 of men 99.9
of men are not on the c-suites of large
corporations
so we're talking about a very tiny
proportion of the population and they're
strange people
right they are they are they're not
normal people
and the reason i say that is because
first of all they're very intelligent
most of them
so so that that that takes the first
slice
and the second slice is all they do
is work like 80 hours a week
and not everybody wants to do that and
and why should they it's like
whoever said that you should work 80
hours a week but if you're gonna rise to
that level in any profession
i don't give a damn what the profession
is if you want to hit the
top one tenth of one percent in your
profession
then all you do is work and not only do
you work you work hard and efficiently
and you do it better than anyone else
plus you need the talent and you need
the intelligence and you need the luck
and you need the health and
all the other things that might go along
with that and so the fact that
a majority of them happen to be men that
that says
nothing about the structural what would
you call this
it says nothing about the fundamental
structure of the state as far as i'm
concerned
and why are we concentrating only on the
upper end
like why is it that it's the ceos that
count and not the bricklayers
you know and when there's all sorts of
things we can talk about with regards to
that that's straightforward okay so
what's the difference between men and
women with regards to occupation
okay men are way more likely to work
outside okay so now
half the women who work outside half the
people who work outside have to be women
men are way more likely to work in
dangerous jobs they're overwhelmingly
more likely to be injured and killed on
the job it's like okay time to equate
for that i don't know exactly how we're
going to do that
maybe we just injure women randomly
until it's equal or we force them to
take the jobs
and i don't know how we do that okay
men are way more likely to move that's
another thing
they're also much more likely to work
longer hours women are way more likely
to work part-time
that's particularly true by the way in
scandinavia and the reason they do that
is because well you know they hit their
30s early 30s usually and they think
especially often if they're successful
i've seen this happen with women all the
time
so i worked with women in in in in law
firms
really unbelievably accomplished women
because the the firms would send us
their best performers and our job was to
see if we could
make them a little bit more productive
because if they were high performers and
they were even five percent more
productive it was unbelievably
valuable for the company and so all the
loft the law firms they just lose
all their women in the 30s in their 30s
and it happens everywhere
and the reason it happens is very
straightforward and all the female
lawyers know this
they won't talk about it publicly but
they all know it
they did very well in high school then
they did very well in university
then they did very well in law school
then they went and articled and they did
extremely well as
articles as articling students then they
got
hired as associates and did very well
and then they made partner
and it was just like linear progression
and there wasn't a lot of questioning
that went along with it because most of
the people
who do that are very conscientious so
they're duty-bound and so you know they
hit it they
they they have an aim and they just
execute man they execute and
conscientiousness by the way is the best
predictor of success
in law after intelligence and so you
have to be a conscientious person
detail-oriented and so
if you happen to be a woman like that
extraordinarily hard-working very very
bright
you just make a beeline to partnership
but then you're 30.
that's a problem and it's a problem for
a bunch of reasons the first is
you've hit the target and now you're
surrounded by these guys
and women who are partners and you
thought that was a hell of a fine place
to be
but when you get there you find out that
it's rough
it's aggressive it's competitive it can
be nasty
and most of the people who are doing it
are not happy
it's hard work i've met lawyers who like
what they're doing but they're rare
it's very competitive and it's very
harsh and
you're going to work man if your parents
get paid 750
an hour you're working whenever there's
work to do
no matter what else you have to do and
you know you might and you might be
making
three hundred and fifty thousand four
hundred thousand dollars a year and
that's good but you're probably married
to someone who's making approximately
the same amount of money
so you actually don't need that much
money and you certainly don't need more
you might want it but you don't need it
and then you start thinking
why the hell would anyone in the right
mind do this
which is the right question by the way
to ask about the people who sit
in the c-suites in major corporations
it's like they're working 70 80 hours a
week for
30 or 40 years you know that often they
sacrifice their families for it and
everything else
and they're they're a particular kind of
person who does that usually hyper
conscientious
but like the question why you would do
that is a really good question
how about you have a life how about you
have a partner that you see sometime how
about you have some children
that you actually get to see and take
care of and so then you think well maybe
i don't need to work 80 hours a week to
continue my rise through the
you know upper strategy stratosphere of
the law profession i'll
pull back i'll find an eight hour a day
job or a for a part-time job
and i'll have a family well that's
what's happening in scandinavia
it's like is that okay or not
and if it's not okay what are we going
to do we're going to enforce we're going
to force gender equality there too are
we
you know they've enforced gender
equality at the
board level in the scandinavian
countries
it hasn't made a goddamn bit of
difference to the number of women who
were in management positions in
scandinavia
and the reason for that was that wasn't
the problem
it wasn't systemic oppression
there's a multitude of reasons that men
and women take different
pathways in their careers and they're
becoming more evident another one is
that
women so women are different
higher in negative emotion higher
agreeableness both the same in
conscientiousness
um openness and extroversion there's
some differences but they're relatively
minor
pretty much the same in terms of
intelligence doesn't look like it's an
ability issue for
for most for most professions with the
exception of the
extended male variability hypothesis
that might have to do with like upper
level mathematical genius but we can
leave that aside
because it's debatable there is a
different other difference between men
and women and this is the biggest
difference that psychologists have
discovered and that's of interest men
are more interested in
things on average and women are more
interested in
people on average and the difference is
actually quite big it's one standard
deviation which means that
it's a little more than that which means
that if you were a man
as interested in people as the typical
woman
is interested in people you would be you
would have to be more interested in
people than 85 percent of men
and if you were a woman who was as
interested in
things as the average man is interested
in things you'd have to be more
interested in things than 85 percent of
women
so it's actually quite a big difference
and so thing
interest is a big determination of
interest in the stem fields
and women just aren't that interested in
things now some of them are and they go
into the stem fields but most of them
aren't
so what are you going to do about that
so you know one of the things they're
trying to do in the in
in the scandinavian countries is they're
going to really start to socialize
boys and girls different in preschool
okay so that's good so that's where
you're going to allow is it this is the
idea
you're going to discount the notion
entirely
that there might actually be differences
between men and women
even though that wouldn't necessarily be
a bad thing but we're going to discount
that
and we're going to assume that all the
differences in outcome are a consequence
of systemic
oppression and then we're going to give
enough power to the state
so that they're going to transform the
way that our children
are treated when they're three and four
by teachers by preschool teachers and
we're going to try to rejig
the entire culture predicated on that
theory
that's the solution well if you don't
think that that's a totalitarian
solution
then you are not thinking
and this is the last one i'll answer a
little ornery about these questions
tonight
apparently what do you think of our
state governments teaching gender
fluidity concepts to primary school
children this is what i think i think if
your damn
primary s school teachers knew how to
teach
kids to read they wouldn't have to
bother teaching gender fluidity
thank you everyone it was a pleasure
talking to all of you
[Applause]
you have a lovely city by the way and
it's been a pleasure being here
good night